## Zsolt István

CONTACT Information  $\begin{array}{lll} {\rm Phone:} \ +34 \ 91\text{-}101\text{-}2202 \\ {\rm Email:} \ zsolt.istvan@imdea.org \\ {\rm Website} & {\rm GoogleScholar} \end{array}$ 

Research Profile My research interests lie in the intersection of distributed systems, databases and specialized hardware. I explore and combine ideas from these areas in order to overcome the compute/data gap that modern data centers face.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Computer Science

2013 - 2018

Systems Group, ETH Zürich, Switzerland

Advisor: Prof. Gustavo Alonso

M.Sc., Computer Science (Distributed Systems)

2011 - 2013

ETH Zürich, Switzerland

B.Sc., Computer Science

2007 - 2011

UTCN Cluj-Napoca, Romania

Professional Experience

## IMDEA Software Institute, Madrid, ES

September 2018 – Present

Assistant Research Professor

Working in the area of distributed systems and hardware acceleration for data processing.

IBM Research, Rüschlikon, CH

May 2018 - July 2018

Visiting Researcher

Topic: Exploring software and hardware acceleration opportunities for Blockchains.

Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA

June 2014 - August 2014

 $Research\ Intern$ 

Supervisor: Ken Eguro

Topic: Adding support for B-tree indexes and a local cache to the FPGA in Cipherbase.

Xilinx Labs, Dublin, Ireland

September 2012 - March 2013

Research Intern (Master Thesis) Supervisor: Michaela Blott

Topic: Design of a hash table for an FPGA-based key-value store optimized for caching scenarios. Helped in overall prototype implementation.

INRIA, Sophia-Antipolis, France

July 2011 - August 2011

Research Intern (OASIS Group)

Supervisors: Ludovic Henrio and Fabrice Huet

Topic: Annotation-based automatic parallelization of Active Objects in ProActive.

INRIA, Sophia-Antipolis, France

June 2010 - August 2010

Research Intern (OASIS Group)

Supervisor: Denis Caromel

Topic: Parallel programming and scheduling for multicores in the ProActive Framework

MaxIQ Computer, Oradea, Romania

2008 - 2009

Junior Software Engineer

Role: Backend (Java EE) and frontend (HTML, Javascript) developer.

#### Conference Publications

## A Flexible K-Means Operator for Hybrid Databases

Z. He, D. Sidler, <u>Z. István</u>, G. Alonso. International Conference on Field Programmable Logic and Applications (FPL), 2018.

Providing Multi-tenant Services with FPGAs: Case Study on a Key-Value Store. Z. István, G. Alonso, A. Singla. International Conference on Field Programmable Logic and Applications (FPL), 2018.

Accelerating Pattern Matching Queries in Hybrid CPU-FPGA Architectures. D. Sidler, Z. István, M. Ewaida, G. Alonso. ACM SIGMOD/PODS Conference (SIGMOD'17), 2017.

### Low-Latency TCP/IP Stack for Data Center Applications.

D. Sidler, Z. István, G. Alonso. 26th Int'l Conference on Field Programmable Logic and Applications (FPL'16), 2016.

### Runtime Parameterizable Regular Expression Operators for Databases.

Z. István, D. Sidler, G. Alonso. 24th IEEE Int'l Symposium on Field-Programmable Custom Computing Machines (FCCM'16), 2016

### Consensus in a Box: Inexpensive Coordination in Hardware

Z. István, D. Sidler, G. Alonso, M. Vukolic. 13th USENIX Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation (NSDI '16), 2016.

### Histograms as a Side Effect of Data Movement for Big Data.

Z. István, L. Woods, G. Alonso. ACM SIGMOD/PODS Conference (SIGMOD'14), 2014.

## A Flexible Hash Table Design For 10Gbps Key-value Stores on FPGAs.

Z. István, G. Alonso, M. Blott, K. Vissers. 23rd Int'l Conference on Field Programmable Logic and Applications (FPL'13), 2013.

## Achieving 10Gbps Line-rate Key-value Stores with FPGAs.

M. Blott, K. Karras, L. Liu, K. Vissers, Z. István, J. Bar. 5th USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Cloud Computing (HotCloud'13), 2013.

Multi-threaded Active Objects. L. Henrio, F. Huet, Z. István. 15th Int'l Conference on Coordination models and Languages (COORDINATION), 2013.

#### Adapting Active Objects to Multicore Architectures.

L. Henrio, F. Huet, Z. István, G. Sebestyen. Int'l Symposium on Parallel and Distributed Computing (ISPDC 2011), 2011.

#### JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

### Active Pages 20 Years Later: Active Storage for the Cloud.

Z. István, D. Sidler, G. Alonso. To appear in IEEE Internet Computing July/Aug 2018.

# Caribou: Intelligent Distributed Storage.

Z. István, D. Sidler, G. Alonso. Proceedings of VLDB Endowment, Volume 10, No. 11 (VLDB'17), 2017.

## A Hash Table for Line Rate Data Processing.

Z. István, G. Alonso, M. Blott, K. Vissers. ACM Transactions on Reconfigurable Technology and Systems (TRETS), March 2015.

Ibex – An Intelligent Storage Engine with Support for Advanced SQL Off-loading. L. Woods, Z. István, G. Alonso. Proceedings of VLDB Endowment, Volume 7, No. 11 (VLDB'14), 2014.

#### Patents

Systems and Methods for Providing Distributed Tree Traversal Using Hardware-Based Processing. K. Eguro, Z. István, A. Arasu, R. Ramamurthy, K. Shriraghav. US 20160147779 A1, Patent application filed 11/26/2014

Posters and Demos

Enzian: a Research Computer for Datacenter and Rackscale Computing.

D. Cock, R. Achermann, M. Owaida, Z. Istvan, T. Grosser, Z. Wang, G. Alonso, T. Roscoe,

D. Sidler, A. Turowski. Poster at EuroSys'18.

Caribou: A Platform for Building Smart Storage

Z. István, D. Sidler, G. Alonso. Poster at EuroSys'17.

doppioDB: A Hardware Accelerated Database

D. Sidler, M. Ewaida, Z. István, K. Kara, G. Alonso. Demo for SIGMOD'17 and FPL'17.

Specialized Microservers for the Data Center

Z. István, D. Sidler, G. Alonso. Demo for FPL'15. Poster at EuroSys'15.

Hybrid FPGA-accelerated SQL Query Processing

L. Woods, Z. István, G. Alonso. Demo for FPL'13.

Teaching EXPERIENCE Teaching Assistant at ETH Zürich

Advanced Systems Lab Fall 2013, Fall 2014, Fall 2015, Fall 2016, Fall 2017

Spring 2016, Spring 2017 Data Modeling and Databases

Programmieren und Problemlösen Spring 2014, Spring 2015

Student Supervision at ETH Zürich

Semester Project: Zhenhao He (co-advised with David Sidler) Spring 2018

Title: A Flexible K-Means Operator for Hybrid Databases

Bachelor Thesis: Mickey Vanska (co-advised with David Cock) Spring 2017

Title: Program Trace Analysis on an FPGA

Bachelor Thesis: Tim Taubner Spring 2015

Title: Accelerating Statistical Methods using an FPGA

Semester Project: Jakub Szymanek Spring 2014

Title: Indexes and Caching in IBEX

Community SERVICE

Reviewer for IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE) (09.2017),

IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS'18) (external),

ACM Journal of Architecture and Code Optimization (TACO) (06.2017).

Shadow PC member for ASPLOS'18, EuroSys'18, EuroSys'17.

SCHOLARSHIPS and Awards

ETH Zürich Excellence Scholarship 2011-2013: Full scholarship for M.Sc. studies

"Grigore Moisil" National Programming Competition (3rd Place), Romania, 2007

Debate – South-East European Youth Leadership Institute (SEEYLI) 2005: Finalist in

Romania; Attendee of summer school at Wake Forest University, NC

Talks

Selected Invited Caribou – Intelligent Distributed Storage.

IMDEA Software Institute, Madrid, Spain. February 2018

KAUST, Thuwal, Saudi Arabia. October 2017

Packing a Punch: Building Intelligent Distributed Storage with Hardware.

TU Dresden, Germany. July 2017

Caribou: Intelligent Storage for the Datacenter.

Swiss Joint Research Center Workshop, MSR, Cambridge, UK. February 2017

Consensus in a Box: Inexpensive Coordination in Hardware.

IBM Research Rüschlikon, CH. October 2016

Accelerating String Matching Queries with Hybrid CPU-FPGA Multicores. Oracle Labs, Belmont, CA. March 2016

Consensus in a box: can we build distributed systems with FPGAs? Xilinx Labs, San Jose, CA. March 2016
IBM Research Almaden, San Jose, CA. March 2016

Time to Specialize! A Microserver for Key-value Stores. University of Washington, Seattle, WA. June 2015

Towards Better Energy Efficiency in Datacenters using FPGAs. Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA. June 2015

Application-specific Micro-servers.

Oracle Labs Zürich Kickoff Workshop, Zürich, CH. January 2015

 $\begin{array}{ll} {\rm LANGUAGES} & {\rm Hungarian,\ Romanian,\ English-Proficient} \\ {\rm German-Intermediate} \end{array}$